Register of the Laurence H. Silberman Papers, 1947-1976
Hoover Institution Archives
Laurence H. Silberman Papers
1947-1976
83031
Hoover Institution Archives
50 manuscript boxes, 1 phonotape, 1 envelope (20.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, studies, testimony, legal documents, printed matter, and photographs, relating to U.S. government domestic policy during the presidential administrations of Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford, labor relations, investigations of the United Mine Workers, equal employment opportunity policies, and judicial proceedings.
Silberman, Laurence H. (Laurence Hirsch), 1935-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical Note
1935 Oct. 12 Born, York, Pennsylvania
1964-1967 Partner, Moore, Silberman and Schulze, Honolulu, Hawaii
1967-1968 Attorney, Appellate Division, General Counsel's Office,vNational Labor Relations Board
1969-1970 Solicitor of Labor, United States Department of Labor
1970-1973 Under Secretary, United States Department of Labor
1973-1974 Partner, Steptoe and Johnson, Washington, D.C.
1974-1975 Deputy Attorney General, United States Department of Justice
1975-1977 Ambassador to Yugoslavia
1977 President's Special Envoy on International Labor Organization (ILO) affairs
1977-1978 Senior Fellow, American Enterprise Institute
1978-1979 Managing partner, Morrison and Foerster, Washington, D.C.
1979-1983 Executive Vice President for Legal and Government Affairs, Crocker National Bank, San Francisco, California
Scope and Contents note
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoranda, reports, studies, testimony, legal documents, printed matter, and photographs, relating to U.S. government domestic policy during the presidential administrations of Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford, labor relations, investigations of the United Mine Workers, equal employment opportunity policies, and judicial proceedings.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1983.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; United Mine Workers of America; United States. Dept. of Justice.; United States. Dept. of Labor.; Affirmative action programs.; Justice, Administration of--United States.; Labor policy--United States.; Phonotapes.; Trade-unions--United States.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1974-1977.; United States--Politics and government.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1966-1975 (Box 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical sketches, clippings, financial documents, memoranda, legal documents, annual report, correspondence, address list, reports, resolutions, agenda, minutes, notes, bulletins, printed material and miscellany primarily relating to personal matters, the American Bar Association, and the 1972 Republican campaign. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - General. Biographical sketches, clippings, personal data and financial statements, legal documents, annual report and a memorandum to George Shultz relating to the Alaska pipeline, 1966-1974
    - Correspondence. Personal correspondence, letters of congratulation, and correspondence of Mrs. Silberman; includes letters from William Rehnquist and Elizabeth Hanford (Dole), 1969-1975 (Folder 2-6)
    - List of addresses, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - American Bar Association
    - General. Correspondence, 1974 (Folder 8)
    - Economic Controls Committee. Reports, agenda, resolutions, minutes, correspondence, notes and printed materials, 1972-1974 (Folder 9-10)
  - Republican Party. Program, miscellany, correspondence, memoranda, bulletins, notes, agenda and schedules primarily relating to the 1972 convention, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1969-1975 (Box 2-7)
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches and writings, with related correspondence, notes and background material. Arranged chronologically.
  - General
    - General. Correspondence, schedules, notes, printed material and other miscellany relating to speaking engagements for which no text has been found
      - 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
      - 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Outlines, notes and drafts. Unidentified texts; includes some fragments (Folder 2)
  - Speech, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - Speech, Letters, typescript drafts, and background materials (orders, regulations, procedures, report, and legal documents) relating to equal employment opportunity policy, 1969 June 18. (Folder 4-5)
  - "Some Observations on Federal Contract Compliance," Typescripts, correspondence, and background material, including testimony by George Shultz, 1969 Aug. 12. (Folder 6)
  - "Labor Policy Under a Republican Administration," Typescript drafts, outline, press release, notes, and miscellany, 1969 Sept. 4. (Folder 7)
  - "The Development of the Administration's National Occupational Safety and Health Bill of 1969," Typescript, letter, memorandum and Senate bills, 1969 Oct. 16. (Folder 8)
  - Testimony, U.S. Senate, Appropriations Committee, Typescript and background material, ca. 1970 Jan.-March. (Folder 9)
  - "National Emergency Disputes--The Considerations Behind a Legislative Proposal," Georgia Law Review, Typescript, letter and printed copies, 1970 Fall-Winter. (Folder 10)
  - "The Search for an Effective Remedy in Employment Discrimination," Draft typescripts, printed copy and meeting materials, 1971. (Folder 11)
  - "Labor as a Factor of National Power," Typescript and correspondence, 1970 Sept. 4. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Labor Relations Outlook for the '70's," Correspondence, typescript and miscellany, 1970 Sept. 17. (Folder 2)
  - Speech, Typescript, statements (George Shultz and others), letters, and printed materials relating to profit-sharing and legislation, 1970 Oct. 22. (Folder 3)
  - Speech, Typescript, letter and memoranda, including a memorandum from Richard Nixon; related to workplace safety, 1970 Oct. 26. (Folder 4)
  - "Proposed Pension Legislation--The Administration's View," Drafts, printed material, letters, press releases, and miscellany, 1970 Dec. 8. (Folder 5)
  - Speech, Outline, letters, speech transcript (George Shultz), press releases, memoranda, and reports relating to farm labor legislative proposals, 1971 Jan. 19. (Folder 6)
  - Speech, Outline, reports and other background material relating to the United Mine Workers, 1971 Feb. 3. (Folder 7)
  - Speech, Correspondence, printed material and an outline relating to farm labor legislative proposals, 1971 Feb. 9. (Folder 8)
  - Testimony, U.S. House of Representatives, Education and Labor Committee, Labor Subcommittee. Correspondence, copies of House bills, and Labor Department proposals relating to equal employment opportunity, 1971 March 3. (Folder 9)
  - "Emergency Disputes and the Public Interest," Press release, typescripts, drafts of a bill, letters and miscellany, 1971 March 18. (Folder 10)
  - Speech, Typescript drafts, press release and miscellany relating to the construction industry, 1971 April 29. (Folder 11)
  - Speech, Outline, clipping, letters and miscellany, 1971 May 17. (Folder 12)
  - "A Government Perspective on the Future," Typescript, letters, memoranda, notes and miscellany, 1971 June 19. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Labor and the Building Team," Typescript, correspondence, outlines, and miscellany, 1971 June 21. (Folder 2)
  - "The New Welfare Reform Bill," Draft typescripts, ca. 1971 July. (Folder 3)
  - Speech, Typescript, correspondence and miscellaneous meeting materials, 1971 July 7. (Folder 4)
  - Speech, Letters, speech transcripts, outline, and a memorandum from the White House, 1971 Sept. 17. (Folder 5)
  - Speech, Correspondence, press release and typescript, relating to employment of offenders, 1971 Oct. 18. (Folder 6)
  - Speech, Letters, typescripts, miscellany and outlines relating to the Nixon Administration, 1971 Nov. 9. (Folder 7)
  - "Pension Reforms: The Administration's View," Letters, typescripts, and miscellany, 1971 Nov. 16. (Folder 8)
  - Speech, Notes, outline, typescript and printed material relating to Phase II of the Nixon Administration's economic policy, 1971 Nov. 17. (Folder 9)
  - Press conference, Transcript relating to emergency strike legislation, 1972 Jan. 21. (Folder 10)
  - Speech, Outline, letter, and miscellany, relating to the West Coast dock strike and economic stabilization policy of the Nixon Administration, 1972 Feb. 3. (Folder 11)
  - Speech, Speech transcript and meeting materials relating to the Manpower Development and Training Act, 1972 March 16. (Folder 12)
  - Speech, Press release, charts, outlines, memoranda and miscellany, 1972 May 8. (Folder 13)
  - "Employment and Manpower Policies for the Future," Notes, correspondence and agenda, 1972 May 18. (Folder 14)
  - Speech, Outline, notes, printed materials, memoranda, press release, and meeting materials relating to Jewish equal opportunity employment, 1972 June 14. (Folder 15)
  - Testimony, Senate Committee on Banking, Housing and Urban Affairs, Subcommittee on Housing and Urban Affairs, Correspondence, typescript and draft speech transcripts, statements and miscellany, 1972 June 20. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "The Research Information Market," Correspondence, speech transcript, clipping, press release, and miscellaneous meeting materials, 1972 June 28. (Folder 2)
  - "Purposeful Communication," Draft speech transcripts and report relating to equal opportunity employment for Spanish-speakers, 1972 Aug. 8. (Folder 3)
  - Speech, Outline, typescript, correspondence, printed copy and background material relating to a proposed bill (S. 2486), and miscellaneous meeting materials; relates to fiduciary responsibility, 1972 Aug. 15. (Folder 4)
  - "Priority Problems for Industrial Relations Executives," Speech drafts and outlines, memoranda and correspondence, 1972 Sept. 26. (Folder 5)
  - Speech, Speech drafts, press release, notes, correspondence and miscellaneous meeting materials, 1972 Sept. 29. (Folder 6)
  - Speech, Notes, briefing paper, and miscellany, 1972 Oct. 4. (Folder 7)
  - Speech, Speech transcript and letters, 1972 Oct. 15. (Folder 8)
  - Speech, Speech drafts, notes, and miscellaneous meeting materials, 1972 Oct. 25. (Folder 9)
  - Speech, Speech notes, press release and miscellaneous meeting materials, 1972 Nov. 6. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Law and the Humanities," Background materials, letter and miscellany relating to a radio broadcast, 1972 Nov. 21. (Folder 2)
  - "The Secretary and the Law: Pre-Balloting Investigations Under the Landrum-Griffin Act," Draft articles and correspondence, relating to the United Mine Workers election and the murder of Joseph Yablonski, 1973 Jan. (Folder 3)
  - "Law and Equality," Broadcast transcript, 1973 Jan. 31. (Folder 4)
  - Speech, Outline, 1973 March 8. (Folder 5)
  - Speech, Outline, printed material and miscellaneous meeting materials, 1973 May 17. (Folder 6)
  - Speech, Speech notes and miscellaneous meeting materials, 1973 June 11. (Folder 7)
  - Testimony, Senate Judiciary Committee, Separation of Powers Subcommittee, Outline, drafts and transcript, letter, and statements relating to the Cost of Living Council, 1973 Oct. 10. (Folder 8)
  - Speech, Speech outline and correspondence, 1973 Nov. 12. (Folder 9)
  - Speech, Memoranda and draft speech, 1974 March 22. (Folder 10)
  - Testimony, House of Representatives, Committee on Government Operations, Subcommittee on Legislation and Military Operations, Typescript, 1974 July 10. (Folder 11)
  - Testimony, Senate Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee on Criminal Laws and Procedures, Typescript, 1974 July 22. (Folder 12)
  - Speech, Typescript and trip miscellany, 1974 July 25. (Folder 13)
  - Testimony, House of Representatives, Government Operations Committee, Legal and Monetary Affairs Subcommittee, Typescript, 1974 Sept. 17. (Folder 14)
  - Speech, Speech transcripts, memoranda and background materials relating to a meeting on Chesapeake and Delaware Bays wetlands conservation, 1974 Sept. 20. (Folder 15)
  - Testimony, House of Representatives, Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee on Immigration, Citizenship and International Law. Typescript, 1975 Feb. 4. (Folder 16)
  - "Illegal Aliens," Typescript, 1975 Feb. 20. (Folder 17)
- UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF LABOR, 1959-1975 (Box 8-45)
  Budgets, memoranda, correspondence, reports, charts, forms, miscellany, press releases, chronologies, legal documents, invitations, agenda, minutes, clippings, telephone logs, appointment books, notes, draft and printed copies of legislation, testimony and speech transcripts, serial issues, notebooks, proclamations, executive orders, pamphlets, regulation and printed articles. Primarily relates to labor issues such as equal employment opportunity, labor-management relations, specific industries, Nixon Administration policy, legislation, and other subjects. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - General
    - General. Printed article, pamphlets, letters and miscellany, 1968-1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Budgets and planning documents. NOTE: most of these have been distributed to the specific departments
      - General. Memorandum and a policy circular, 1970 (Folder 2)
      - FY 71. Memoranda, budget and letter, 1970 July-1971 March (Folder 3)
      - FY 72. Memoranda, correspondence, reports and charts (primarily with the Office of Management and Budget), 1970 July-1971 Dec. (Folder 4-5)
      - FY, 1973
        - General. Memoranda, 1970 Sept.-1972 Sept. (Folder 6)
        - Legislative program. Reports, proposals and memoranda, ca. 1972 Sept. (Folder 7)
      - FY 1974. Memoranda, reports, and charts, 1971 June-1972 Oct. (Folder 8)
    - Calendars
      - 1970 July-1971 June (Folder 9-10)
      - 1971 July-1973 Jan. (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
    - Confirmation materials
      - General. Forms, memoranda, and miscellany, 1970 Sept.-Oct. (Folder 4)
      - Briefing materials
        - General. Press release, memoranda, printed materials, correspondence, statement, forms, chronology of United Mine Workers litigation, and reports; relates to Mr. Silberman's position on a number of labor issues, 1969-1971 (Folder 5)
        - Notebook. Relates primarily to the administrative responsibilities of the Under Secretary, 1970 (Folder 6)
      - Transcripts. Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, 1970 (Folder 7)
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - General. Primarily personal material such as letters of congratulation, thanks, and recommendations; includes correspondence with Senator Hiram Fong, Maurice Stans, William Ruckelshaus, George Shultz and others, 1969 March-1973 Jan. (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
        - Invitations. Includes a letter from Gov. Jimmy Carter
          - 1970-1972 (Folder 5-6)
          - 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
      - American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO), 1970-1972 (Folder 5)
      - Civil Service Commission, 1970 Sept.-1972 Aug. (Folder 6)
      - Environmental Protection Agency, 1972 (Folder 7)
      - General Services Administration, 1970-1972 (Folder 8)
      - Health, Education and Welfare Department, 1970-1972 (Folder 9)
      - Javits, Senator Jacob K., 1971-1972 (Folder 10)
      - Justice Department, 1970-1972 (Folder 11)
      - Massachusetts, State of, 1972 (Folder 12)
      - Office of Management and Budget, 1971-1972 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Pennsylvania, State of, 1972 (Folder 2)
      - State Department, 1970-1973 (Folder 3)
      - Thurmond, Senator Strom, 1971-1972 (Folder 4)
      - United States House of Representatives, 1971-1972 (Folder 5)
      - United States Senate, 1969-1972 (Folder 6)
    - Investigations. Memoranda and correspondence with Richard Kleindienst, the Civil Service Commission, the White House and others, 1970 July-1972 Nov. (Folder 7)
    - Meetings
      - General, 1969 Aug.-1972 Feb. (Folder 8)
      - Conferences. Includes meetings at Camp David and San Clemente, 1969 May-1972 May (Folder 9-13)
      - Regional visits, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      - Staff meetings, 1970 June-1971 Nov. (Folder 3)
    - Memoranda
      - General
        - General. Notebook of notes and memoranda, probably collected by Laurence Silberman during his legal career in Hawaii, ca. 1961-1966 (Folder 4-5)
        - Includes memoranda to the White House and other agencies, although primarily consisting of material within the Labor Department, 1969 May-1973 April. (Folder 6-7)
      - Secretary of Labor, 1970 Sept.-1972 June (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - White House. Includes reports, press releases, draft correspondence and other miscellany, 1968 Dec.-1972 Dec. (Folder 2)
    - Notes, 1970-1972 (Folder 3)
    - Personnel
      - Labor Department
        - General. Printed material, charts, memoranda, and letters, 1969-1972 (Folder 4)
        - Actions (reclassifications, promotions, and other), 1969-1972 (Folder 5)
        - Applicant materials, 1971-1972 (Folder 6-7)
        - Appointment materials
          - General. Miscellaneous forms, press releases, memoranda and notes, 1970-1972 (Box 15, Folder 1)
          - Silberman, Laurence. Includes a clipping, a press release and a resignation letter, 1969-1972 (Folder 2)
        - Executive Staff Manual, 1972 March (Folder 3)
        - Memoranda. Relating to personnel policy (Folder 4)
        - Recommendations, 1971-1972 (Folder 5)
        - Report. Relates to Labor Department personnel management, 1971 (Folder 6)
      - White House. Recommendations and resumes, notes, memoranda, letters and charts, 1970-1972 (Folder 7)
    - Telephone logs and memoranda
      - 1970 July-1971 April (Folder 8-9)
      - 1971 May-1973 Jan. (Box 16, Folder 1-5)
    - Trip material, 1969-1971 (Folder 6)
  - Agriculture
    - General. Memoranda, letters and notes, relating to farmworkers, unemployment compensation, health and safety and other issues, 1969 Jan.-1972 Aug. (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Grape boycott. Letters, printed materials, meeting minutes, affidavits, press releases, investigation reports, and legal documents, 1960 March-1970 March (Folder 2)
    - Legislation
      - General. Notes, memoranda, reports, chart, draft legislation and letters relating to proposals to amend the National Labor Relations Act to form a national agricultural labor relations board, 1970 Dec.-1971 Aug. (Folder 3)
      - S. 2203, "Consumer Agricultural Food Protection Act of 1969". Bill, memoranda, testimony transcripts (George Shultz and others), letter, and a press release, 1969 May-1970 Aug. (Folder 4)
      - H.R. 7597. Relates to bargaining. Bill and analysis, 1971 April-May (Folder 5)
  - Alien employment
    - General. Correspondence relating to immigration quotas, a legal case, and individual labor certifications, 1970 Aug.-1972 Oct. (Folder 6)
    - Mexican migrant laborers. Press release, notes, serial issues, statement and memoranda; includes material generated by the AFL-CIO, SEE ALSO: JUSTICE DEPARTMENT/Border study, 1969 Feb.-1972 Sept. (Folder 7)
  - Bureau of Labor Statistics. Letters, memoranda and reports, 1970 July-1973 Jan. (Folder 8)
  - Child labor. Press release, memoranda, and report; relates to agricultural child labor and training programs, 1969 Sept.-1971 Sept. (Folder 9)
  - Commerce Department
    - General. Memoranda and correspondence, 1970 July-1972 June (Folder 10)
    - Minority Business Enterprise program. Correspondence, reports and charts, 1971 Nov.-1972 Dec. (Folder 11)
  - Construction industry
    - General
      - General. Report, memoranda, correspondence, speech drafts, 1970 July-1972 Nov. (Folder 12)
      - General Presidents of the Building Trades. Newsletters, draft and final statements, correspondence and memoranda relating to labor endorsements for Richard Nixon, 1972 Sept.-Nov. (Folder 13)
    - Affirmative action
      - General. Printed material, correspondence, memoranda, press release and statutes, 1966 May-1973 Jan. (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Philadelphia Plan. Notebooks of collected materials, ca. 1969-ca. 1970 (Folder 2-6)
      - Collective Bargaining Commission
        - General. Directory, memoranda, reports, speech transcript, letters, 1969 June-1972 Oct. (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
        - Vocational Education Subcommittee. Correspondence, directory, and background materials for a meeting, 1970 Nov.-1972 Aug. (Folder 3)
      - Construction Industry Stabilization Committee
        - General. Proclamation, statement by Richard Nixon, correspondence, press releases, agenda, printed material, memoranda, and proposals, 1971 March-Dec. (Folder 4-5)
        - Reports. Primarily settlement reports, including some case summaries and charts, 1971 June-Dec. (Folder 6)
      - Davis-Bacon Act
        - General. Memoranda, charts, pamphlets, a briefing notebook prepared for hearings by the Senate Subcommittee on Housing and Urban Affairs,; relates to wage rates on federally-funded construction projects, 1970 Oct.-1972 Aug. (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
        - Suspension. Press releases, field reports, letters, printed material, memoranda, H.R. bill, statement and proclamation by Richard Nixon, 1969 Oct.-1971 March (Folder 4)
        - Reinstatement. Memoranda, press releases, reports, printed material, telegram, letter, proclamation and statements, 1971 March-Aug. (Folder 5)
  - Economic stabilization. Primarily relates to the activity of the Nixon Administration Cost of Living Council
    - General
      - General. Status reports and summaries, questions, press conference transcripts, proclamations, pamphlet, speech transcripts (Richard Nixon and Henry Jackson), chart, newsletter, statements (AFL-CIO and Secretary of Labor Hodgson), executive orders, draft bill, and printed material
        - 1969 Nov.-1971 Nov. (Folder 6-7)
        - 1971 Nov.-1972 March (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Clippings and wire stories, 1971 May-Sept. (Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, 1970 July-1973 March (Folder 3)
      - Meetings. Assembled materials from Cost of Living Council meetings, including agenda, minutes, and memoranda on litigation and policy issues
        - 1971 Aug.-1972 April 20 (Folder 4-10)
        - 1972 April 26-Aug. (Box 22, Folder 1-7)
      - Memoranda, 1971 Feb.-1973 Dec. (Folder 8)
      - Policy papers
        - General
          - General. Primarily a notebook (?) relating to organized labor, pensions and the military, 1971 Aug.-Oct. (Folder 9)
          - Press releases. Summary of Cost of Living Council decisions, 1971 Aug.-Oct. (Box 23, Folder 1)
        - Exemptions. Cost of Living Council reports, charts, memoranda and press releases, 1971 Aug.-1972 March (Folder 2)
      - Press releases. Primarily questions and answers; also includes some internal memoranda, 1971 Aug.-Dec. (Folder 3-4)
    - Office of Emergency Preparedness
      - General. Memoranda and letters, 1971 Aug.-1972 Nov. (Folder 5)
      - Press releases, 1971 Aug.-Nov. (Folder 6)
      - Regulations. Printed material from the Federal Register, 1971 Aug.-Oct. (Folder 7)
    - Pay Board. Report, memoranda, letter, and press releases, primarily relating to policy, 1971 Oct.-Dec. (Folder 8)